Rhiannon: Each time a new medication
is prescribed, a doctor or other
professional will not know how well it
is going to work until the individual
has been taking it for a while.
It will also be difficult
to predict whether they will
suffer from any side effects.
Not all medication works for every
person and many medications take
time to start working and longer
to reach their full potential.
Leah: All medications have side
effects, but not everyone gets them,
and each person is affected differently.
Some side effects improve or go
away over time, some don’t happen
straight away, and some may seem as
bad as the illness being treated.
Rhiannon: An individual may need to try
a few different medications and different
dosages before they find the right one.
Medication used to treat depression
for example, normally takes a few weeks
to start having a beneficial effect.
Leah: In most cases an individual has a
choice not to take a medication if they
don’t want to, but it can be worth a
try, to see if it can help and getting
a parent or carer to give support
and understand the treatment plan,
gives it the best chance of success.
Rhiannon: If an individual’s mental
health problem is severe, it may be
that they ‘have to’ take the medication
to maintain good mental health.
If medication works and makes improvements
to mental health, repeat prescriptions
will be issued, but regular monitoring
and occasional checkups will follow.
Leah: To find out more about different
medications available, and what they
are prescribed for, you can go to the
following link for further information.
http://youngminds.org.uk/youngminds-professionals/our-projects/headmeds/